<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue between Simeon and Levi upon this topick, whether flying from suffering in a day of persecution, or complying with the terms of the persecuting party for a little ease, be the more honourable.</title>
            <author>Nicholets, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08712971</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08712971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35889)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1256:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue between Simeon and Levi upon this topick, whether flying from suffering in a day of persecution, or complying with the terms of the persecuting party for a little ease, be the more honourable.</title>
                  <author>Nicholets, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Charles Nicholetts--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Persecution.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:41634:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi.</hi> Upon this TOPICK, WHETHER Flying from Suffering, in a Day of Perſecution; Or, Complying with the Terms of the Perſecuting Party, for a little Eaſe, be the more Honourable.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>With Allowance.</p>
            </argument>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>WEll met, Brother <hi>Simeon,</hi> after ſo great a Storm. The Blaſts of <hi>Boreas</hi> have blown fierce upon us. The Elements have been black over, us; and nothing but the hideous noiſe of Thunder-Claps have been heard among us. But now, through the Clemency of our Gratious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41634:2"/>
there is a great allay. The Clouds are ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the fury of the Wind is over; the Air is calm and ſerene, and we being ſo happily met under a ſhadowing Tree, in this pleaſant bright day, pray let us ſit down and talk a little.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Simeon,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>With all my heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Then, how has it been with you all this time? how have you ſecured your ſelf from the terrible ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that have been every where? I ſee you look pritty brisk and bonny, which makes me conjecture you have not felt much of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, truly, no Brother; I have not; for in its firſt appearance (which was ſo gaſtly, it made me tremble) I finding my ſtrength to decay, betook me to the Country; where I lived, private, and in quiet, from the noiſe and clamours of all ſuch things.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>But had you not a Paſtoral charge of a Flock?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I had ſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>How then could you leave them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I wiſely fore-ſaw, the rage of the Storm growing ſo great, that every one would be forced to ſhift for himſelf; and I was willing to ſave one betimes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Methinks you have not acted like a good, but bad Shepherd, whoſe proper Charector is, when he ſees the Wolf coming, to fly away, and leave his Sheep to be devoured.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I confeſs that looks a little awry upon me; but I have a plain Text to bear me out in what I have done.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Pray tell it me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, if they Perſecute you in this City, flee into another.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Without the help of <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Cup, I divined
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41634:2"/>
what your Scripture would be. But you cannot ſurely think this any warrant at all for your practice: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that, this was ſpoken to Apoſtles, who had no care of any particular people: So it is meant of a flying only from ſuffering (which may be innocent) but not from work, which is your caſe; you (<hi>Jonah</hi> like) fled from your Paſtoral Employment, to live Solitary in the Woods, to keep your skin whole.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, I will not ſtand in it, but I have done amiſs; but of two Evils, I thought t'was prudent to choſe the leſſer; if I had ſtayed, I might have gone to Priſon and dyed (oh! terrible) as ſome other did, and ſo have been of no uſe now: Whereas I was ready, upon the firſt news of his Majeſties Indulgence (and as ſoon as I heard the Coaſt was clear of Informers) to pack up my Auls, and away to</hi> London, <hi>with as much ſpeed as ever I tripped from it, (which was ſuch, as I aſſure you ſecured me from the fate of</hi> Lot's <hi>Wife) and to reparing my waſted Synagogue I went; raiſed up the Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, jumbled together the Pews, and ſold them too, as faſt as I could tole in Cuſtomers; (for I had a pannick fit of Zeal freſh come upon me to do my Maſters work) and am now as hard at it as ever, and thump it about, as in the days of yore, and mean to continue ſo till—But pray, now you have examined me; give me leave to demand, where you have ſanctuaried your ſelf; for you look as though you had born as little of the brunt as I?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Why, truly when I firſt ſaw the Clouds a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, I buckled on my Helmet, advanced my Voice, and ſtanding is the high Place of the Tabernacle, I ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly warned my People, with ſtretched forth Lungs, to prepare for the approaching Storm, and to be ſure to ſtand to their Tackling, and not baſely deſert the Cauſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41634:3"/>
as they would avoid another day the forever odious name of Renogadoes; and this I continued with much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to do, till I was unhappily ſeized, and caſt into Bondage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh! ſad</hi> (Horriſco audiens)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>But I tell you (for the encouragement of all that dare try it a little while: for I am not for long Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment) I had a great deal of comfort, and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the time of my Captivity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>As how I pray?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Many ſweet doſes of glittering Guineys for a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial in a morning; ſundry pretty Angels miniſtring to my neceſſities on high noon, when Colon began to grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and ſeveral Noble treatments attended my accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at night.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If I had known this, I would not have fled ſo faſt from a Priſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Ay, But Brother, you muſt know there was an ebbing tide in thoſe Enjoyments (as there is in all created Comforts) the Springs of Conſolation too ſoon (Ah, I tell you, too ſoon) abated of their Exuberancy; and then (ah then, my Strength fainted, and my Spirit no longer able to bear up) failed within me; then every thing in a Priſon ſeemed diſſatisfactory to me, and then it was I began to groan for Liberty; 'tis true, I had Friends in a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oundance came to viſit me, but they were dry (therefore miſerable) Comforters, Words flowed with a mighty torrent from their Mouthes, but there was no dropping at their Fingers ends, from whence I always derived the moſt Satisfaction and Encouragement: I tell you Brother, one good well-mannag'd Pocket-Argument ever had more prevalency with me to perſevere, then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41634:3"/>
an hundred airy Throat ones; for whilſt I was boye<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up by the former, I ſtoutly affirmed (with no want o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Confidence) the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be Abominable, the Frame of her Conſtitution wholly diſ-agreeing to Goſpel Light and Truth; but when thoſe Supports ſhrunk from me, I ſoon alter'd my Opinion, I got a new pair of Spectacles, and read over the <hi>Comon-Prayer;</hi> and truly I could find nothing but good and ſound matter in it; and ſo without further conſideration, I reſolved <hi>(rebus ſic ſtantibus)</hi> to yeild a profound Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to it, which I forthwith promiſed, and then with winged Celerity, I bid my Priſon, my Keeper, my People, my Integrity an entire farewel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Had you not better have gone into the Country as I did?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>No, I thank you, I made a better Market of my ſhort Impriſonment; I might have followed the Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail long enough, before I ſhould have met with thoſe feeling Contentments I did there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which of us was the honeſter Man?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I can't tell that, but I think we have neither of us much to ſpare of that Commodity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which of us took the more honourable Way?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>That muſt be left to the Judgment of ſome Learned Brethren, who are not altogether unacquainted with either of our ways.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What will the Men of the World ſay of us?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>I know what they ſay of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>A Man may take a great deal of pains for God, in a fine cool day, when 'tis neither too hot, nor too cold; He may lay about him much, even to a mighty thumping
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41634:4"/>
the innocent Pulpit, making the Feathers lead a wearied life for want of a little reſt; He may be very Induſtrious and Laborious; He may Preach much, Pray much, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techize much, and yet when it comes to the pinch, and there be moſt need of his work <hi>Doe-Little.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Say you ſo Brother; Ay, but do you know how the Carnal ſort ſpeak of you?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Deliver me out of pain, inform me quickly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, they (that is, the Sons and Daughters of Men) ſay very peremptorily, A Man may Bluſter and Thunder, lift up his Voice like a Trumpet, Roar like a Wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd Bull of</hi> Baſhan, <hi>lay about him like a Tbraſher, Whine and Cry, Baul and Yaul, Preſs and Perſwade his Auditors to ſtand their Ground, and not comply in the leaſt with ſinful Traditions; and yet, when it comes to his own particular Caſe, to Buckle or Suffer, even ſuch a one may ſhew himſelf, (to his never to be forgotten ſhame) <hi>Non Vincens ſed Victus.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>We can't help it, I wiſh they have nothing more to ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do you think they will be tattling any thing elſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>Yes, Yes, no doubt they will draw ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Inferences from both our Practices: As 1ſt. True Zeal to God can't be meaſured by Mens keeping a noiſe, when they have nothing to oppoſe them, till they come to the tryal of a ſuffering Teſtimony. 2dly. They will be apt to conclude, that unleſs <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath ſome faithfuller Workmen, then you or I have appeared to be, his Work will certainly be left undone, when there is the moſt need of doing it. 3dly. I am afraid they will infer, that as our Saviour choſe to ride upon a ſimple Aſs, rather then a trapped Horſe; ſo (according to the truth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41634:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the Myſtery) he calls out poor low Men (that are little eſteemed by the World) to bear the burthen of his Service, in the day when he has moſt ſervice to do. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> 'Tis ten to one but thoſe, who are not Followers of us, will be ſurmiſing, our preſent hot-ſpur re-aſſumed Zeal, proceeds rather from a love to our dearly beloved ſelves, and our own Intereſt, then any true deſire of advancing Chriſts mediatory Kingdom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are baſe Inferences, and yet too natural. But Pray, let us meet ſuddenly again to diſcourſe of our Friends of the Congregational way, to remark how they have carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in the time of Perſecution, whether like us or no?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Levi,</speaker>
               <p>I fear (upon examining the matter) we ſhall find a vaſt difference.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Sold at the <hi>Three Kyes</hi> in <hi>Nags-Head-Court</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Conduit,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
